foreign
so this is a suitor from angutsu nikaya
1065. and
and
somebody is asking
venable sariputta
what is happiness and what is suffering
and he replies birth is suffering
no birth is happiness
when there is birth you can expect this
kind of suffering
cold heat hunger thirst
defecation and urination
contact with fire sticks and knives
and relatives and friends get together
and annoy you
when there is birth this is the kind of
suffering you can expect
when there is no birth you can expect
this kind of happiness
no cold heat hunger thirst defecation or
urination no contact with fire sticks or knives
no contact with fire sticks or knives
and relatives and friends don't get
together and annoy you when there is no
birth this is the kind of happiness you
can expect
but there is no birth
there is no birth
so yeah so what is how should then birth
be understood
that's the point
you know the
life taken personally
yeah well
that which is born
taken personally
the buddha describes birth as coming out
of womb and manifestation of the
aggregates into this world
but people seem to sort of
misconstrue that in a sense that
they think that manifestation ended once
you came out of womb
no that's birth and it still is
jaati yeah jaati the manifestation that
you are now
is all due to you coming out of the womb
so
all of this now heat cold relatives all
of that is that birth it's because of
that birth
so the birth is not
uh confined to like a little
moment that lasted for like i don't know
half an hour on average or an hour
no manifestation persists
because of the birth and the birth is
the manifestation so for as long as
you're manifested you are born
in the same sense like
i don't know you enter this country now
you cross the border
the fact that now wherever you are here
you are within the country because you
cross the border because you entered it
so you are manifested here now and i
don't need to find out
where you crossed the border and how and
how long it lasted or or observe it the
fact that you're inside here inside of
this country i know that you have you
must have crossed the border so you were
born so your manifestation is what your birth
so your manifestation is what your birth
is
that's when participant partner when one
is sort of
freed from ignorance he frees himself
from birth you can't undo coming out of
womb but you can undo appropriation and
but you can undo appropriation and
ownership of that manifestation which
was your birth which was through your
birth which was because of your birth
which is what your birth is
practically speaking people
would you know
wander because often jaat is mentioned
because often jaat is mentioned
earth is mentioned in the suttas birth
is suffering yeah birth is suffering
exactly and all the suffering is
birth aging sickness and death that's
all because of the
assumptions and
tank and so on
so it's like if birth is that physical
coming out of war if it's confined to
that only
how can you undo that you can't
so you then subject it to all of this
because well first of all you don't even have a
well first of all you don't even have a
memory of your own birth
you haven't seen yourself
coming out of boom you don't you don't
recollect that
so if that's your birth truly if it's
only confined to that
event it's utterly inaccessible to you
it's utterly inaccessible to you
something that you can understand let
alone abandon
but if you take birth to be
much broader phenomenon such as ah this
manifestation that endures here sickness
aging cold elements words of others that
is basically manifested here aging and
so on ah that's the birth that's because
of the birth that's what birth is
being born means being manifested so for
as long as that manifestation endures
your birth is there
so you can then address that directly
by yeah uprooting the ownership of it
by seeing that
everything that's within that
manifestation everything that manifests
whatever has the nature of manifestation
cannot be yours because of that because
it has arisen on its own and so on so
you are subjected to birth exactly
objective to aging subject fundamentally
you're subjected to that not knowing
that you're subjected to aging birth
elements annoying relatives
annoying relatives
you take the ownership
you assume it's yours you assume it's
you you assume it's for you either way
it's yours and because of that
you suffer on account of it and
everything that pertains
to that manifestation
will be affecting you
right but if you
don't take it personally
but both the manifestation of advocates
i like can i say your life
that's enough well yeah your life is the
manifestation your life is which is
manifested in the broadest sense
so how can you then
disown your life
without destroying it
because you can see
that you can see that birth as the
is that that
phenomenon that you are subjected to
like i didn't choose to be born there
wasn't a point
so this manifestation that you find in
the world
your form that it is you
so to speak
you had no say in it at all
and so all these little projects my
wishes and dreams and all my little
things i'm doing or issues or
cold heat and so on
when seen in that
light of that greater context of birth
being not being my mind yeah then
everything all the little things that
are inside it are not
yeah yeah they were faded yeah because
that's the problem really the problem is
that despite
despite
the obvious that you had no say
in your form
in your birth in your overall set of
aggregates you you were subjected to it
people still assume the ownership of it
and perpetuate that ownership through
acting out of
those that very form seeking pleasure in
form as the buddha would say
as if it is theirs so they know it's not
this but when the pleasure presents
itself you act as if it is yours
you don't care in other words so you act
out because you can
in other words you're borrowing
something because it's free
ignoring the fact that well it's still
borrowed so sooner or later you have to
pay for it
so that's why it's always compared to
the modest trap and similar
so you have to refrain from borrowing
that which you know it's not yours what
is not yours i is not yours ears nose
mouth body
feelings are not yours thoughts are not
yours but you're taking them as yours
because you can
so to speak
so that's why i have to contemplate the
danger to do to undo that attitude of
oh i'll just take this because i get a
quick pleasure through it quick
satisfaction quick
to satisfy my desires
so you have to see the danger to prevent
yourself from borrowing that which you
know you shouldn't
from taking the ownership of that which
you know you deep down you don't really
own but if you if you now see that that uh
but if you if you now see that that uh
non-ownership in the context of
non-ownership in regards to birth
this manifestation
you you develop that perception
you develop that perception
from time to time and make it steady
compose yourself in it
[Music] then you
then you
i mean if maybe before you do that you
would think
now you're not going to really
try to develop you do anything in your
life you know you're not going to
because life is not mine
you know well i don't have to take
responsibility you know i just wrote
it down relax
that's the of course that's anything
even the most accurate of the
instructions can be taken wrongly if
people don't develop the right attitude
they need to look for faults and if they
look for escape from responsibility so
you can't possibly address that you
can't possibly say well yeah you know
how can we prevent that from happening
because that's that's up to people to
decide so
all of the instruction presupposes that
the person who is listening to this
is authentic wants to be free from
suffering has already taken
responsibility for their own situation
and is not trying to avoid it and wants
to find the solution that they can
develop their freedom from suffering
but a person doesn't have that attitude
yeah i mean the buddha himself can be
speaking and people will just hear what
they want to hear to justify what they
want to order the job why they justify
already before for themselves and avoid
the responsibility for it so
so you don't have to be you know
throwing things away destroying your
body well no exactly yeah that might be like
well no exactly yeah that might be like
the first thing
yeah but it's like well so you're
destroying someone else's property now
so if it's not
yours why do you think you have a right
to destroy it either
not borrowing it does not mean
destroying it but yes people will
destroy it because
for as long as it's there it's tempting
me to borrow it well that's the catch
to learn how not to borrow it
now to destroy it so you're not tempted
then you borrowed it you have to pay for
it because you destroyed it plus you're
not using it either you broke it you
bought it you bought it yeah yeah that's
exactly so how to be in the world how to
be in the world and not be
with the world uh
please sit
thoroughly taken seriously seeing the
danger in the slightest fault is what it
says guarding of the sensors we spoke about
guarding of the sensors we spoke about
right often so it's not like i adhere to
these precepts because i'm buddhist or
something no i adhere to these pieces
because they're prerequisites for
containing my mind that needs training
and that training starts to
be put in place
through sensory strength and guarding of
the sensors so
that's for example like when something
is not against the precepts
but you still don't necessarily do it if
you know that it's rooted in desire
mentally so you guard your sense those
because that's where the problem is oh
is this rooted in a wholesome desire or
not not is this according to the letter of
not is this according to the letter of
the rule or not that's how you start but
if you actually want to practice out of
it
you have to take it up from that in
personal mechanical observation
observances and make it make it like take
and make it make it like take
responsibility for it so i keep the
precepts because i want to develop the
mind and i also got the sense restraint
oh god that sends those and practice
sense restraint on account of the same
thing so
it's not an offense to i don't know
eat between 8 and 12 in the morning
between 8 and 12 in the morning
but
again how much i eat
what i eat why i eat
uh
half then i that period all of that is
not against the precepts but it can very
much still be the behavior that feeds
your desire if you don't check that as
well so you guide your sense those
so you guide your sense those
and your your moderate and you also
practice sensory strain within the
creases that you already keep
so that's how you basically fortify
yourself uh against the direction and the pull of
uh against the direction and the pull of
the world so you're in the world but not
with that world on the same level
and it's the same whether you're a monk
or not
okay yeah
but you also you have to be
uh contemplating the danger in their
world then as well well yeah that
contemplation i mean
will be sort of you'll be revolving
around that one way or the other
like if you already
had enough let's say determination to
take on the precepts
and decide to practice out of them
yeah that's already implies exactly some
recognition of danger of not doing so
danger of going back to the to the
previous state of non restraint and so
on
so yeah that's how you will basically
uh as i said fortify your mind and then
all these things that we talk about
non-ownership and seeing the greater
context well then that can actually
arise can be seen
now you people would not necessarily be
able to see it because the mind is still
far from that necessarily that
necessarily developed basis for it it's
not dry enough from sensuality it's not
withdrawn enough from
company independence and others and so
on you you can't see the
those the signs and features exactly exactly
the signs and features exactly exactly
yeah
the signs and features that we recently
spoke about yeah they haven't been
developed sufficiently
so
the the context is only limited
it doesn't mean that it's wrong what
that person might be understanding but
it's not sufficient so you need to now
that context that you have developed you
need to now broaden it even further find
a greater context to that that you can
then sustain yeah that's something so if
you understand
or you can actually um
be aware of the context of
charity of birth yeah being present yeah
what is greater than what it what um
surrounds that what context amongst that
and i would say that you know that's the
i would say that you know that's the
um the context of death
yeah but what's implicit in the manifestation
but what's implicit in the manifestation
is the cessation of manifestation yeah
so
no matter how
wonderful your life is
or how many things you're doing or not
doing it's just going to
it's just going to
yeah it's on the basis of manifestation
that you have no saying that has its own
direction and expiry date
and you're not privy to that it's
inaccessible to you
so you want to see the front of it given
to you
and if you so that then if you in now
now you you develop in the context of
death on only but you have to first develop
on only but you have to first develop
the context of
yeah exactly yeah yeah yeah you like
context context of death is developed
correctly mindfulness of death is
practiced correctly only
if the the extent of life is seen for
what it is
and then in that sense you
when you understand the context of death
then then
you depend well then expression is the
result for life yeah
it's also what we do next nothing
sustain that and you will approve any
passion desire ill will irritation
ownership resistance and so on
expectations in regard to any
manifestation whatsoever
so whatever has the nature to manifest
that's why it has an age to cease that's
it
but as you're saying so you're not going
to get to be able to see that
great uh phenomenon of charity or birth
if you not don't have a clear mind yeah
exactly this isn't going to be like an abstract
this isn't going to be like an abstract
idea
um but the more it's not like and
sometimes people might actually yeah
sort of get the idea but then
recognize that it's abstract and then
they think oh so now i need a new idea
or a better idea no now you need to
elevate your mind to meet the abstracted
idea so it ceases to be abstracted from
it
so you need to bring your mind to where
that idea is not change the idea to fit
where your mind is
and you bring it again
to virtue sense restraint moderation
watchfulness and so on
the direct training
that also implies responsibility you
cannot irresponsibly
guard the sensors
you cannot irresponsibly say no to your
central desires
because lack of responsibility is tied with the
lack of responsibility is tied with the
desire with saying yes with the flow
going with the grain
so if you are practicing sense restraint
and moderation and watchfulness that
implies responsibility reflection
exactly so the more you develop it the
more of that reflexive recognition of
that responsibility you will have
oh i just carelessly irresponsibly
said no to sensuality that's impossible
that is impossible you would have to
in a way you are keep asking yourself
what am i responsible for
you know
i'm responsible for choosing well that's
for action yeah what am i responsible
for it doesn't need to be anything
specific i'm responsible for accepting
this manifestation of this birth right
yeah for acting out of it as if it's
minor as if it is my am i responsible
for for
for
creating birth exactly i'm not
responsible for the manifestation of it
i'm not responsible for these
liabilities of cold hunger so on or
whatever else bothering me and i'm not
responsible for that but i'm responsible
if i take up the ownership of this form
that that's experiencing all of that
so that's how you then become invested
in fearing cold heat elements
misfortune craving for pleasure craving
for escape craving for cover-ups
ill will towards people they don't know
you and so on
because you took the ownership of the
basis that's subjected to those things